听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
在本节课的最后一部分
In the last part of this lecture,
我们将考虑分布式系统中可能出现的
we are going to look at the relative ordering of different messages and different events
不同消息和事件的相对顺序问题
that can happen in distributed system,
以及我们如何在这个场景下使用时间
and how we might use time in this context.
我们仍然以一个例子来开场
So, let's start with an example again.
我们先来考虑一个例子：通过互联网开一个讨论线
Let's start with an example of a discussion thread on the Internet.
一种典型的荒谬讨论是 一个用户说
And one of those typical highbrow discussions where one user says
“月亮是奶酪做的！”
“The moon is made of cheese!”
另一个用户响应说
and another user responds to them saying
“不 你错了！”
“No, you are wrong!”
我们来为这个讨论线建立一个模型
So, we are going to model this kind of discussion thread here.
假设用户A说“月亮是奶酪做的！”
Let's say we have user A here who says “The moon is made of cheese!”,
将消息m_1发送给用户B和用户C
sends that message m_1 to users B and C.
我们这里使用一个常见的系统模型
And we're going to just assume our usual system model of,
这是一个可靠网络连接
let's say, reliable network links.
但消息可能会出现时延 消息可能会出现乱序
but messages might be delayed or might be reordered as usual.
可能出现的一种情况是 用户B很快收到了消息m_1
And so, it can happen that user B receives message m_1 fairly quickly,
用户C等了一会才收到了这条消息
and user C receives that message a little bit later,
这是因为网络出现了一点延迟 这种情况很常见
just because it's been delayed a bit in the network. That's fine.
随后 用户B响应消息1
Now, then, user B responds to message 1.
用户B收到m_1 随后说“不 月亮不是奶酪做的！”
User B receives m_1, and says “No, the moon is not made of cheese!”
将这句话作为消息m_2发送给用户A和用户C
and sends that as message m_2 back to user A and also to user C.
现在 你可以从示意图看到
Now, what can happen is what you see in this diagram here is that
用户C在收到m_1之前先收到了m_2
user C actually receives m_2 before receiving m_1.
这令人非常苦恼 想象一下 当用户C看到这条讨论线时
And this is kind of confusing because if you imagine user C is looking at this thread,
用户C先看到“不 不是这样的！” 再看到“月亮是奶酪做的！”
user C first sees “Oh no, it isn't!”, and then “The moon is made of cheese!”
即使“不 不是这样的！”
So, even though “Oh no, it isn't!” really
应该是用来回复“月亮是奶酪做的！”
should be a reply to “The moon is made of cheese!”
但这里出现了消息乱序的情况
we have ended up reordering those.
我们在得到被回复的消息前先收到了回复的消息
And we've got the reply before the thing that it's replying to.
这令人非常苦恼
This is pretty confusing.
我们来想一想 我们如何形式化描述这个问题
So, let's think about how we might be able to formalize this problem,
我们如何构建一个算法来解决这个问题
and how we can create algorithms that solve this problem.
解决此问题要基于一个事实：一件事情一定是另一件事情发生后才发生的
So, this is based on this idea that one thing happened before another.
我认为我们可以同意m_1一定在m_2之前发生
I think we can agree that m_1 happened before m_2,
因为如果m_2是m_1的响应 那么肯定要先发生m_1
because if m_2 is a response to m_1, then m_1 must have happened first.
系统内存在一些逻辑时间
There's some kind of logical time in the system here.
我们来看看 如果我们在每条消息中附加上时间戳 则会发生什么
But let's see what happens if we attach timestamps to each message.
当用户A发送消息m_1时
So, let's say that when user A sends message m_1,
用户A使用自己的本地时钟生成一个时间戳t_1
user A also uses A's local clock to generate a timestamp t_1,
并将时间戳t_1附加在消息m_1上
and attaches that timestamp t_1 to the message m_1.
随后 当用户B收到m_1并发送m_2时
And then, also, when user B receives m_1 and sends m_2,
用户B从自己的本地时钟得到一个时间戳t_2
user B gets a timestamp t_2 from B's local clock,
将此时间戳附加在消息m_2上 并把消息发送给其他两个节点
and attaches that timestamp to the m_2 message that is sent to the other two nodes.
现在 我们假设这些时间戳表示的是现实世界的日历时钟
And now, we're going to assume that these are of course physical time-of-day clocks.
我们假设时钟已经通过NTP等协议完成了同步
We're going to assume that the clocks are synchronized using something like NTP.
但是 即使时钟已经经过了同步
But it could still happen even if clocks are synchronized,
时间戳t_2也可能会小于时间戳t_1
it could happen that the timestamp t_2 is actually less than the timestamp t_1.
这确实有可能发生 因为同一系统中的两个节点可能会存在时钟偏移
This could happen because the clock skew between two nodes in a system
两个节点的时钟偏移量可能会大于两个节点之间的单向网络延迟
might be greater than the one-way network delay between those two nodes.
即使经过了NTP同步 我们仍然无法排除
And even with NTP synchronization, we cannot rule out the possibility that
时钟偏移量大于单向网络延迟的这种可能发生的情况
the clock skew is greater than the one-way network latency.
在我们的这个场景下 可能出现的情况是 m_1经历了一些延迟
And so, in this case, here, m_1 is experiencing some kind of latency,
但延迟小于用户A和用户B的时钟偏移量
but that latency is smaller than the clock skew between users A and B.
在这种情况下 如果用户B的时钟跑得稍微慢了一点
And in that case, if user's B clock is running slightly behind
用户A的时钟跑得稍微快了一点
and uses A's clock is running slightly fast,
此时的结果就是 t_2小于t_1
then you could end up with t_2 being less than t_1.
我们这个练习的总体目标是
And so, our whole aim of this exercise was to
保证消息可以根据发生的时间正确排序
ensure that messages get put in the right order according to time.
但即使在这里使用时间
But even using time here,
我们仍然不能按照正确的发生顺序放置消息
we have not actually been able to put the messages in the right order,
因为不同节点的时间戳顺序
because the timestamp order is inconsistent
与我们理解的消息请求和回复顺序是不一致的
with our understanding of which message is a reply to which the other message.
如何解决这个问题？
So, how do we solve this problem?
在分布式系统中
What we do in distributed systems is
我们解决此问题的方法是使用此前发生关系
we use something called the happens-before relation.
这是为分布式系统中可能发生的活动
And so, this is a mathematical model of activity
所定义的一个数学模型
that has happened in the distributed system.
当我们讨论分布式系统中的可能发生的活动时
And so, when we're talking about activity in a distributed system,
我们首先需要定义什么叫“发生了一件事情”
first of all, we need to define what are the things that happen.
我们把“发生了一件事情”称为事件
So, we'll say the things that happen are events.
事件可以是：系统中的一个节点在本地执行了一个步骤
An event can be just one node in the system making a local execution step,
一个节点做了一些事情 这属于一个事件
one node doing something, that can be an event,
事件也可以是：一个节点向另一个节点发送了一条消息
or an event could be a message that one node sends to another.
发送一条消息也属于一个事件
So, the sending of the message is one event,
接收一条消息是另一个事件
and then, the receiving of the message is another event.
如果一条消息到达了某个参与方处 接收此消息属于另一个事件
If the message arrives, then the receiving would be another event.
现在 我们可以把关系定义为包含一系列事件对的集合
And so now, we can define a relation which is a set of pairs of events
每个事件对都描述了事件的相互关系
that describes how those events relate to each other.
如果a在b之前发生 则此前发生关系写为a→b
And this happens-before relation is written as a a→b if a happened before b.
我们称如果发生了下述三种情况之一 则a→b
And we say that a→b if at least one of three things is true.
第一种情况是 a和b这两个事件在同一个节点中发生
So, the first thing is that the two events a and b happened in the same node,
且在此节点的本地执行顺序中 a在b之前发生
and a occurred before b in that node's local execution order.
我们这里假设每个节点是单线程处理任务的
So, that means we are here assuming that each node is a single threaded process
即先完成一件事情 再完成另一件事情
that is just doing one thing after another.
当单节点内仅包含单线程时
So, there's no ambiguity about the order
此节点就不会有模糊的顺序定义了
in which things happened on a single node if there's a single thread.
事情只能一件一件地发生
Then, things only happen one after another,
我们可以准确定义哪件事情先发生 哪件事情后发生
and we can define exactly which thing happened first and which happens second.
对于每一个节点
So, we're going to assume that for each node,
我们都假设此节点的事件发生顺序都是严格有序的
there's a strict total order of all of the events that happened on that particular node.
如果我们确实希望此数学模型支持多线程处理
If we did want to support multi-threaded processes,
则为了满足模型的定义
then we could have each thread being a separate node
我们把每个线程都看成独立的节点
for the purposes of this model here.
我们现在只假设单线程的情况
So, we can just assume single threads for now.
这样一来 我们就可以称
And so, we're going to say that
如果a和b发生在同一节点上 且a在b之前执行 则a→b
a→b if they happened on the same node and a was executed before b.
这是一个合理的定义
That makes sense.
第二种情况是 我们称a→b
Secondly, we're going to say that a→b
如果事件a是发送特定的消息m
if a is the event that a certain message m was sent,
而事件b是接收相同的消息m
and b is the event that this same message was received.
为了消除第二种情况中可能出现歧义的情况
So, for the purpose of making this unambiguous,
我们必须假设每条消息都是独一无二的
we have to assume that messages are unique, because otherwise
否则可能会出现两个不同事件发送了同一条消息的情况
you could have two different events for the sending of the same message,
当然了 实际系统中肯定会出现这种情况
which, of course, could happen in a real system,
但这种情况会使模型在数学上变得难以描述
but it makes the thing difficult to model mathematically.
为了简化描述 我们假设发送的每条消息都是独一无二的
So, for simplicity's sake, here we just assume that every message that is sent is unique.
如果我们想在实际中让每条消息变得独一无二
And if we wanted to actually make messages unique in practice,
我们可以在每条消息上附加一个顺序值
we could attach some kind of sequence number
并在消息上附加发送此条消息的节点标识符
and the identifier of the node that sends the message.
我们可以在每条消息上都附加节点标识符和顺序值
For example, we could attach that to every message,
我们也可以在每条消息上附加一个很长的随机数
or we could pick a long random number for every message,
这就足以让每条消息都变得独一无二了
and that would be sufficient to make every message unique.
第二种情况描述的此前发生关系也是合理的
And so, again, this happens-before relationship makes sense,
因为消息只有在被发送后才可能被接收
because a message can only be received after it has been sent.
因此 在接收特定消息之前认为此特定消息先被发送了出来
And so, it makes sense for the sending of that particular message to happen
这种关系是合理的
before the receipt of that message, OK?
这就是满足此前发生关系的前两种情况
So, those are the first two clauses of happens before.
第三种情况非常简单 如果我们能找到某个事件c 使得a→c且c→b
The third is simply if we can find some event c such that a→c and c→b,
则一定满足a→b
then it must also be the case that a→b.
第三种情况只是定义了前两种子句的传递性
So, this is simply taking the transitive closure of the first two points
将此前发生关系扩展为满足偏序性
and extending the whole thing into what is called a partial order.
偏序性有点类似于两个事物的小于关系
So, a partial order behaves a bit like a less-than relationship between two things.
偏序性允许你比较两个事件 知道哪个事件先发生
So, it allows you to compare two things and say which one happened first.
但有些事件可能无法比较先后关系
But there might be some things that are incomparable according to this order,
两个事件既不满足a→b 也不满足b→a 这两个事件没有先后关系
where it is not the case that a→b or b→a, the two are simply unrelated.
有些情况下 两个事件的发生顺序没有先后关系
It is not the case that either one happened before the other.
此时 我们称a和b是并发的
And in that case, we say that a and b are concurrent.
我们用两个竖线的符号‖来描述事件的并发关系
And we write it with this little double bar, this ‖ here.
这里有个很有意思的结论
So, this is interesting here.
对于任意两个事件a和b 可以证明这两个事件只有三种可能的关系
Now, for any two events a and b, it turns out that there are only three possibilities,
或者a→b 或者b→a 或者a‖b
either a→b, or b→a, or a‖b.
讲义中的一个习题就是让你来证明
And one of the exercises in the notes asks you to actually prove the fact that
两个事件之间只有三种可能的关系
these are exactly the three possibilities that can happen.
我们来看此前发生关系的一个例子
So, let's look at an example of the happens-before relationship.
图中 我们用小黑点表示事件
So, here, we've got events are represented as these little black blobs,
和之前一样 我们用箭头表示在网络中发送的消息
and messages are sent over the network with these arrows as usual.
这个例子中有三个节点
And we've got three nodes here.
接下来
And so,
我们要应用独立的子句构造此前发生关系
we're going to build up the happens-before relationship from the individual clauses.
第一 根据特定节点的事件发生顺序
And so, firstly, due to the order of events happening in a particular node,
节点A在b之前执行a 因此a→b
well, here, node A executed a before b, therefore, a→b.
节点B在d之前执行c 因此c→d
Node B executed c before d, so, therefore, c→d.
节点C在f之前执行e 因此e→f
And node C executed e before f, so, therefore, e→f.
目前为止 一切清晰
OK, so far, so clear.
第二 根据消息的发送和接收顺序
Secondly, now, due to messages sent and received,
消息在接收之前应该先被发送出来
the sending of a message happens before the receipt of that message,
因此b→c 因为网络中传输了消息m_1
so, therefore, b→c, because that is message m_1 traveling over the network.
同样地 d→f 因为网络中传输了消息m_2
And also, d→f, because that is message m_2 traveling over the network.
现在 我们得到了部分事件的此前发生关系
So now, we've got all of these relationships between some of the events.
我们再用子句传递性对所有关系进行扩展
Now, we extend this whole thing with the transitive closure.
举个例子 根据子句传递性 a→c且a→d
And so, due to the transitive closure, for example, a→c and a→d,
本质上 你可以想象在图中取得事件发生的一条路径
essentially, what you can imagine here is we can take a path through this graph.
你可以想象每个节点上的事件沿路径依次按时间发生
You can imagine any path that moves forward in time on a node
或者各个节点上的消息按照路径依次发送和接收
or that moves from the sending of a message to the receipt of that message,
消息从一个节点移动到另一个节点
and then moves through other nodes.
你可以在图中选择一条路径
And you can take any path through this graph
沿路径依次按时间移动
as long as you're always moving forward in time,
这样就能从事件a开始 依次向下发生其他的事件
then you will get from any a that happened before any other event.
举例来说 你可以从a走到f 即a→f
And so, here, for example, you can get from a all the way to f, a→f,
因为你可以通过传递两条消息从a走到f
because you can go from a to f by traversing these two messages sents.
但你不能从a走到e
But, for example, you cannot get from a to e,
因为从a走到e要求倒转节点C的事件发生顺序
because going from a to e would require going backwards in the node order of C,
我们不允许发生这种情况
and that would not be allowed.
这也就意味着a‖e
And so, that means that, for example, a‖e.
不满足a→e 也不满足e→a
So, a did not happen before e, e did not happen before a.
这两个事件是并发的 这两个事件相互独立
The two are simply concurrent, which means they are independent.
发生其中一个事件时不需要知道另一个事件是否已发生
One event did not know about the other when it happened.
并发与同步不是一个意思
Concurrent does not literally mean simultaneous.
并发并不是说两个事件要在同一时间发生
It doesn't mean happened literally at the same instant in time.
并发只意味着两个事件在发生时不需要知道另一个事件是否已发生
It just means the two events did not know about each other when they occurred.
因此 a‖e 且b‖e
And so, therefore, a‖e, b‖e.
a、b、c、d和e都满足并发关系
All a, b, c, and d, they're all concurrent to e.
但e和f不满足并发关系 因为用户C定义了e和f的发生顺序
But e and f are not concurrent, of course, because of the order on user C.
这就是此前发生关系
So, that's the happens-before relation.
此前发生关系与分布式系统中的因果关系
And the happens-before relation is very closely connected to
有着非常紧密的联系
the concept of causality in distributed systems.
如果a→b
In particular, if a→b,
这意味着a导致了b的发生 或a在某种程度上影响了b的发生
then it might be the case that a caused b, or a influenced b in some way.
因此 a和b之间存在某个信息流
So, there's some information flow that has happened from a to b,
如果a和b是并发的
whereas if the events a and b are concurrent,
我们知道a不可能导致b的发生 b也不可能导致a的发生
we know that a cannot have caused b, and b cannot have caused a,
两个事件之间没有因果关系
there's no causal relationship between the two.
因果关系的概念来自于物理学
So, this concept of causality is actually taken from Physics,
人们通过因果关系描述空间距离很远的事件发生关系
where typically people reason about events that happen far apart in space,
事件发生的传递时间就是光在两个事件空间距离上传递的时间
and the time that it takes is the speed of light to travel between those things.
如果在不同的星球上、甚至在不同的星系上
So, if you have two events happening on different planets, say,
发生了两个事件
or even in different galaxies,
两个事件的空间距离很远
and so, they are very far apart in space,
但这些事件几乎是同时发生的
but you could have those events happening around about the same time.
这些事件不一定严格在同一时间发生
They don't have to be exactly at the same time,
它们可能会几乎在同一时间发生 但事件之间的空间距离很远
but they're happening fairly close together in time, but fairly far apart in space,
此时 我们就可以绘制出这个空间-时间示意图了
then we can draw this space-time diagram here.
我们可以绘制这样一个示意图
So, we can draw this diagram where
想象一下 当事件a发生时 你从事件a发出了一束光
imagine that you send out a beam of light from event a at the time when event a occurs,
你将这束光发送至周围所有的方向
and you send it out in all directions.
随着时间从上到下移动 空间从左到右移动
And so, then, as time goes here downwards, and space is from left to right,
这束光以光速向空间传播
so, this light just spreads through space at the speed of light,
我们把光的传播范围称为光锥 任意在光锥内发生的事件
and any event that happens within this cone here, this is called a light cone,
这些事件的发生可能都依赖于a的发生
that event might somehow be dependent on a.
但你可以看到 b在a的光锥之外
But you can see b here is way outside of the light cone of a.
同样地 a在b的光锥之外
And also, a is outside of the light cone of b.
因此 当b发生时
So, the information from b at the time when b occurred
b的信息不可能在a发生之前传递到a
could not possibly have got to a by the time a happened.
类似地 当a发生时
And likewise, the information when a happened
a的信息不可能在b发生之前传递到b
could not possibly have got to b by the time b happened,
原因很简单
simply because
此类信息的传播速度要大于光速
that would have required information to travel faster than the speed of light.
据我们所知 在我们的宇宙中
And as far as we know, in our universe,
信息的传播速度不可能大于光速
it is not possible for information to travel faster than the speed of light.
因此 这里的事件c可能受a或b的影响
So, this event c here, for example, that could be influenced by a or b,
但b和a不可能相互影响
but b and a cannot influence each other.
这个来自物理学的概念
And so, this concept from Physics
与我们在分布式系统中引入的概念非常类似
is very closely related to what we have in distributed systems.
在分布式系统中 我们一般会讨论消息在网络中传输
In distributed systems, we typically talk about messages flowing over a network
而不是讨论光在宇宙中传播
rather than light traveling through the universe,
但本质思想是一样的
but essentially, it's the same idea,
这两种思想都是在描述事件是否可能会互相受到影响
it's reasoning about which events could possibly have affected each other.
一旦我们定义好了潜在的因果关系和此前发生关系
And once we have got this potential causality and this happens-before relationship,
我们就可以给事件排序了
we can now order events.
回忆一下我们的例子 先发生了“月亮是奶酪做的！”
And so, remember in our case of first “The moon is made of cheese!”,
随后是回复“不 不是的！”
and then the reply to it “Oh, no, it's not!”,
我们想要的是
what we want is
“月亮是奶酪做的！”要在对话线中先出现
for “The moon is made of cheese!” to come first in this order of the conversation thread,
随后 对话线中再出现回复
and then, the reply to come second in that order.
两个事件存在因果关系
And here, because we have a causal relationship
“月亮是奶酪做的！”的消息m_1
between m_1, which is “The moon is made of cheese!”,
和回复m_1的m_2
and m_2, which is the reply to m_1,
这两个事件存在因果关系
so, there's a causal relationship between the two.
因此 a→b 即m_1→m_2
And so, therefore, a→b, m_1→m_2,
我们想要的是
what we want is that
对话线中的消息放置顺序应该与事件发生顺序保持一致
any order that we put the messages into should be consistent with that.
也就是说 只要a→b 那么根据因果顺序 a应该在b之前发生
So, whenever a→b, then a occurs before b in that causal order.
这叫做因果顺序
This is called a causal order,
即按照一定的顺序放置系统中的事件
that is, it's a way of putting the events in the system into an order in such a way that
使事件满足因果关系
they are consistent with causality,
如果一件事情在另一件事情前发生 则它们也应该按照此顺序出现
that is, if one thing happened before another thing, then they appear in the correct order,
但如果两件事情是并发的 它们可以按照任意顺序出现
but if two things are concurrent, then they could appear in either order,
因为一件事情可能在另一件事情发生前发生
because one could have happened before the other,
我们无法确定哪件事情先发生
there's no real way of saying which one happened first.
此时 两件事情出现的顺序可以是任意的
So, in that case, they could be ordered arbitrarily.
这是一个非常有用的概念
So, this is a very useful concept.
我们将在下一节课使用这个概念
And we're going to use this in the next lecture
后面 我们要在此前发生关系的基础上
when it comes to building upon this idea of the happens-before relationship,
构建可以实现此前发生关系的分布式算法
and making some actual distributed algorithms that implement this.
我想指出的最后一点是
The last thing I will just point out is
很容易混淆“因果”（causal）和“偶然”（casual）这两个词
it's very easy to confuse the word causal with the word casual,
因为这两个词只是中间的两个字母顺序不同
because just two letters are swept around.
我自己也会再三检查拼写是否正确
I keep having to double check it myself as well.
大家在使用时要注意一下
So, just that as a little detail to watch out for.
如果你在撰写分布式系统相关的内容
If you're writing about distributed systems,
你要用的可能是“因果”而不是“偶然”
you probably mean causal, not casual.
下节课见
So, see you next time.